Finding Aid for St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1834-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1834-1998
St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
86890 Ba 2; BA Outsize
Ann Arbor, Michigan Episcopal Church; vestry and parish records, liturgical materials, Christian service and educational materials, administrative records, printed material, and photographs.
17.5 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
1 oversize bundles
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the records were deposited by the church (donor no. 4441 ) in 1978 and 2010. Some early records and the records of the Hobart Guild were deposited by the Harris Memorial Trust Fund (donor no. 1087 ) in 1940.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
St. Andrew's was established somewhere between late 1827 and early 1828. Among Episcopal parishes in Michigan, St. Andrew's is second only to St. Paul's Cathedral in age. The first church building was consecrated in 1838, but by 1855, the congregation had outgrown these facilities and plans were begun for a new "early English," stone church. Consecrated in 1867, St. Andrew's is the oldest church building in continual use in Ann Arbor. A tower, a chapel wing, and an apse were added in the latter part of the nineteenth century. A parish hall, housing a chapel, class and meeting rooms, and offices, was added in the 1950s.
St. Andrew's serves the city of Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan community from location close to the campus and the business district. The growth of the city, particularly after the second World War, led to the founding of two parochial missions which are now St. Aidan's and St. Clare's Churches.
The significant number of students and faculty of the University of Michigan in the congregation led to the founding in the 1880s of Harris Hall, an Episcopal center on the edge of the campus. The Episcopal Student Foundation, with its own board and funding, continues the Episcopal Church's campus ministry from Canterbury House.
St. Andrew's has a tradition of community involvement. The parish was a founder and a significant supporter of the Ann Arbor Interfaith Council of Congregations and is a continuing supporter of minority-initiated projects and such organizations as the Ann Arbor Interfaith Council for Peace. St. Andrew's was responsible for the beginning of the Shelter Association of Ann Arbor, which provides housing and other services for the homeless; and the parish hosts a daily breakfast in its parish hall.
St. Andrew's Episcopal Church has created a rich body of material which documents both its own history and its place within the history of Ann Arbor. The records of the parish have been arranged into nine series: Vestry; Registers; Church Programs; Administrative Records; Scrapbooks; Diocese of Michigan and other non-parish material; Liturgical Materials; Publications; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Children.; Churches.; Clergy.; Easter.; Gillespie, George De Normandie, 1819-1909.; Interiors--Churches.; Lewis, Henry, 1893-; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Northside Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Religion.; St. Aidan's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Religion.; Weddings.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Vestry
  The Vestry series includes minutes of the regular meetings and of the annual parish meeting. This series dates from 1843 and runs to the late 1980s. Also included are annual reports.
  - Minutes and annual parish meetings
    (some annual parish meeting reports filed separately)
    - 1843-1865 (Box 1)
    - 1865-1898 (Box 1)
    - 1898-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1954 (Box 2)
    - 1955-1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 4)
    - 1971-1977 (Box 5)
    - 1978-1983 (Box 6)
    - 1984-1989 (Box 7)
    - Notes of Vestry meetings made by Roger Barney 1971-1979, 4 packets (Box 7)
  - Annual parish meeting reports
    - 1956-1959, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - 1961-1969 (lacks 1960), 9 folders (Box 8)
    - 1981-1987 (lacks 1983) (Box 8)
  - Register of voters for Vestrymen 1935-1945 (Box 8)
- Registers
  Scattered throughout the collection is material of value to the genealogist. Of particular use are the parish registers (ca. 1824-1875) which include records of baptisms, marriages, deaths, and communicants in the period of 1824 to 1877. Later records remain with the church.
  - Record book 1844-1877 (Box 8)
    (include some records of baptisms, marriages, deaths, communicants, etc.; also some published materials)
  - Parish register: include membership information, candidates for confirmation, baptism, etc. 1860s-1870s (Box 8)
  - Parish register: include record of baptisms, marriages, burials, communicants, etc. 1862-1875 (Box 8)
  - Registers of services
    - 1949-1951 (Box 8)
    - 1952-1962 (Box 8)
- Church Programs
  The Church Programs series documents some of the outreach efforts of the church and its mission to the students of the University of Michigan through the Hobart Society.
  - Christian Service material
    - Fellowship committee
      - Welcome booklets (Box 9)
      - Parish directories (Box 9)
    - Refugees committee (Box 9)
    - Welfare work (Box 9)
  - Educational material
    - Sunday school reports 1862-1874 (Box 9)
    - Student programs
      - St. Andrew's Church Society of the University of Michigan 1869-1875 (Box 9)
      - Hobart Society
        - Executive committee 1888-1902 (Box 9)
        - Register 1888-1897 (Volume 1)
        - Secretary's record 1885-1894 (Box 9)
        - Secretary's record 1905-1915 (Box 9)
        - Girl's club 1908-1914 (Box 9)
        - Library shelf list (Box 9)
        - Scrapbook 1886-1904 (Box 9)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      - Episcopal Student Foundation (Box 9)
      - Harris Memorial Trust (Box 9)
      - Student Directories and Harris Hall Brochure (Box 9)
    - Adult programs (Box 9)
- Administrative records
  The Administrative series include correspondence, records of pew rentals and parish supporters, files relating to the building, to pledge campaigns, and to various men's and women's organizations.
  - Correspondence
    - 1834-1862 (Box 9)
    - 1930 (Box 9)
    - 1931 (Box 9)
    - 1932 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Commendatory letters
    - 1860-1874 (Box 9)
    - 1889-1891 (Box 9)
    - 1892-1895 (Box 9)
    - 1896-1902 (Box 10)
    - 1903-1905 (Box 10)
    - 1906-1908 (Box 10)
    - 1909-1911 (Box 10)
    - 1912-1915 (Box 10)
    - 1916-1918 (Box 10)
    - 1919-1921 (Box 10)
  - Pew Rents and Parish Supporters
    - 1849 (Box 10)
    - 1896-1897 (Box 10)
    - 1897-1898 (Box 10)
    - 1901-1903 (Box 10)
  - Church construction
    - Parsonage and church bell circa 1840 (Box 10)
    - Parish hall and chapel 1949 (Box 10)
    - Parish house 1950 (Box 10)
  - Proposed sale of Harris Hall circa 1945 (Box 10)
  - Annual Pledge campaign material
    - 1928 (Box 10)
    - 1932 (Box 10)
    - 1935-1939 (Box 10)
    - 1941 (Box 10)
    - 1945 (Box 10)
    - 1947 (Box 10)
    - 1948 (Box 10)
    - 1949 (Membership gifts) "The Memorials & Gifts at St. Andrew's Church" (Box 10)
    - 1951 (Box 10)
    - 1952 (Box 10)
    - 1955 (Box 10)
    - 1956
      - Minutes (Box 10)
      - Well's Clients School program (Box 10)
      - Pledges (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous material, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - 1957 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous nineteenth century records
    - 1835-1839 (Box 10)
    - 1840-1845 (Box 10)
    - 1840-1848 (Finance committee) (Box 10)
    - 1850-1860 (Box 10)
    - 1854 (church repairs) (Box 10)
    - 1862-1863 (Box 10)
    - 1869 (history of church) (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Parish organizations
    - Church Works Association 1866-1874 (Box 11)
    - Young Ladies Aid Society 1876-1878 (Box 11)
    - Ladies Aid Society of St. Andrews
      - 1896-1910 (Box 11)
      - 1911-1916 (Box 11)
      - 1917-1928 (Box 11)
    - Brotherhood of the Episcopal Church 1914-1917 (Box 11)
    - Men's Club (Box 11)
  - Special Events
    - 125th Parish anniversary/30th anniversary of Rev. Henry Lewis' Ordination, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Newspaper clipping (Box 11)
  - Parish histories (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
- Scrapbooks
  The parish scrapbooks are a very useful compilation of documents and information going back to the earliest days of the church. Many original documents and now obscure newspaper articles found their way into the scrapbooks. A large number of the weekly parish bulletins published during the 1920's and early 1930's are also in the scrapbooks.
  - Founding-1894, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - 1895-1904, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - 1905-1912 (Box 11)
  - 1913-1922, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - 1923-1925, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - 1926-1930, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - 1931-1933, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - 1934-1943 (Box 12)
  - 1944-1949 (Box 12)
  - 1949-1954 (Box 12)
  - 1954-1956 (Box 12)
  - 1890-1904 (Box 12)
- Diocese of Michigan and other non-parish material
  The Diocese of Michigan and other non-parish material series is comprised of records collected but not created by St. Andrew's. These concern primarily the relationship of the church with the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan. Within this small series are materials from the annual conventions of the Diocese of Michigan and a few sermons of Bishop Richard S. Emrich.
  - Annual Conventions of the Diocese of Michigan miscellaneous
    - 1938 (Box 13)
    - 1939 (Box 13)
    - 1946 (Box 13)
    - 1948 (Box 13)
    - 1949 (Box 13)
  - Sermons of Bishop Richard S. Emrich (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Diocese of Michigan material (Box 13)
  - Catalogue, Theological Seminary of the Diocese of Virginia 1844 (Box 13)
- Liturgical material
  The liturgical material is mainly dated during or after World War II, although some items that predate the war are included. Numerous sermons are included in this series.
  - Sermons
    - 1919, 1931, 1934 (Box 13)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 13)
    - 1985-1995, 11 folders (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - By Henry Lewis (Box 13)
  - Advent and Christmas (Box 13)
  - Lent (Box 13)
  - Holy Week (Box 13)
  - Nineteenth Century programs (Box 13)
  - Wartime (W.W. II) Liturgies and Prayers (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous prayers (Box 13)
  - Lectures on the Liturgy (Box 13)
- Publications
  Among the church's publications, the most interesting is an extensive run of the weekly parish bulletin and the church's newsletter.
  - Weekly bulletin
    - 1922-1951, 11 folders (Box 14)
    - 1952-1973, 11 folders (Box 15)
    - 1974-1996, 11 folders (Box 16)
  - Weekly Children's bulletin 1940-1947, 1952-1953, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - "A Letter from St. Andrew's" 1957-1961, 5 folders (Box 17)
  - "Cross Currents" 1962-1969, 8 folders (Box 17)
  - Newsletters, etc. 1935-1974, 1978-1998, 20 folders (Box 17)
- Photographs
  The photographs are of church activities, including worship, weddings, and social activities, activities involving University of Michigan students, and portraits of clergy and parish members. There are also a few photos of Northside Presbyterian Church/St. Aidan's Episcopal Church, Ann Arbor, Mich.
  - Activities
    - Adults (Box 18)
    - Children (Box 18)
    - Choirs (Box 18)
    - 125th anniversary (Box 18)
    - University students (Box 18)
    - Worship and associated activities (Box 18)
  - Bishops of Michigan (Box 18)
  - Building
    - Exteriors (Box 18)
    - Exteriors (other than St. Andrew's) (Box 18)
    - Interiors (Box 18)
    - Windows (Box 18)
  - Clergy
    - Gillespie, George D. (Box 18)
    - Lewis, Henry (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Groups, Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Individuals, Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 18)
  - Northside Church (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous
    (include clippings of photographs from church and other publications)
    - Activities (Box 18)
    - Bishops, clergy, groups, individuals (Box 18)
    - Building (Box 18)
    - Autographs of clergy removed from scrapbook (Box 18)
  - Snapshots taken of areas of the church building needing repair and / or restoration, 1 folders; 1 oversize bundles (Box 18)